All right, so let's talk about the
different types of contracts now.
Now for the PMP exam, there are just three
types of contracts that you need to know.
Just three types with some variations of
each one.
So you have the fixed price contract,
you have the cost reimburse bill contract,
and you have the time and material
contract.
So these are just the three that you need
to know for the PNP exam.
And then there's some variations of each
one.
In reality, there are many many types of
contracts.
In reality, contracts can be a mixture of
other contracts as well.
But specifically for the PMP exam, these
are the only three that you need to know.
Fixed price, cost-reimbursable, timer
material, and some variations of each one.
And so we're going to cover each of these
types of contracts in separate videos.
In this video, we're going to cover the
fixed-price contract.
Now, the fixed price contract,
also known as the FP or the FFP firm fixed
price, there are different
variations of fixed price
contract, which we'll
discuss in just a second.
But in a fixed price contract,
the seller has agreed to provide the
entire good or service at one fixed cost,
one fixed cost to the buyer.
So the seller is going to come in,
do the work.
it doesn't matter how
much it cost the seller, the
buyer is just going to
pay this one fixed price.
That's it.
This is one fixed cost.
And that fixed price, then, that fixed
cost includes all equipment, supplies,
labor, raw materials, all of their
expenses, and then plus their profit.
And so in this case, then, the buyer
doesn't care what the cost is going to be.
The seller is the one
that's controlling all
of the costs because
it's just one fixed price.
So if halfway through the project material
prices go up, too bad for the seller.
They have to absorb all of that cost.
If they underestimated the amount of
labor, too bad for the seller.
They have to absorb all of that cost.
So in this type of contract then,
who has all of the risk of the contract?
Well, naturally the seller.
The seller is going to have all of the all
of the risk of the contract.
Because, as I said, the buyer doesn't
really care about the cost.
The buyer is not controlling the cost.
The seller has to control the cost.
As far as the buyer
is concerned, they just
know that they have to
pay this one fixed cost.
As long as they don't change the scope of
the project, as long as nothing changes,
the seller is just going to
come in, do the work, and
the buyer is just going to
pay them this one fixed cost.
Now, out of all the different types of
contracts end, One of the features on a
fixed price is it has to have the most
detailed statement of work.
So this is a kind of
contract that is going
to have the most
detailed statement of work.
And why?
Well, because both buyer and seller need
to know down to the granular level.
Exactly, what is included, what is not
included?
What is a seller performing?
What is a seller not performing?
What's been delivered?
What is not being delivered?
what is in scope what is not in scope both
buyer and seller need to have a detailed
understanding right of the scope of the
project and so it has to have the most
detailed statement of work out of all the
different types of contracts that we're
going to be discussing now just a couple
of other features on a fixed price first
of all when do we use a fixed price
contract and this again is from a buyer's
perspective right so from PMI's
perspective and a buyer's perspective,
when should we be utilizing a fixed price
contract?
And these are really the scenarios that
you're looking out for on the exam.
So typically on a PMP exam, they'll give
you a scenario and then they'll say what
kind of contract should you use in this
situation.
So these are the kind of scenarios you
have to look out for to distinguish or to
determine that a fixed price contract
would be the best one.
So first of all, you want to reduce the
risk to your organization.
Remember, the seller has all of a risk,
right?
The seller is the one that's controlling
the cost.
The seller has all of the risk in a fixed
price contract.
So if someone there's questions,
someone in this scenario, it says,
you know, your organization is
risk-averse, or you're trying to reduce
the risk to your organization,
then you would use a fixed-price contract.
Also, you'd use a
fixed-price contract when
you know what the outcome is going to be.
It is a well-understood project.
Requirements are well-defined,
right?
Or you know exactly
what the outcome is going
to be, exactly what the
scope of the project is.
It's a well-understood project,
then you can use a fixed-price contract.
If you have no idea what the outcome is
going to be, if you have no idea of what
the costs might be, then you can't really
do a fixed-price contract at that point.
It's only really for something that's
well-understood.
You can't have any cost ranges.
I mean, by definition, fixed price means
you cannot have a cost range, right?
And then also, contract administration is
so much easier, right?
Contracted administration becomes a lot
easier because, as far as the buyer is
concerned, they don't need to worry about
tons of invoices and tons of receipts and
verifying receipts with
the raw materials and
equipment and, you know,
other work that they've done.
No, I mean, again, the buyer doesn't
really care.
The buyer just wants that work done.
The seller is the one that's coming in,
doing the work.
They give them a single invoice and the
buyer pays that invoice.
So these are some of
the reasons then why we
would want to negotiate
a fixed price contract.
Now, a couple of variations of a fixed
price.
So these are three variations that you
need to know for their PMP exam.
So the first one then is FFP, the firm
fixed price.
Now, what we were just talking about just
now, regarding the fixed price contracts,
that was referring to an FFP, a firm fixed
price, right?
It's a firm, it's fixed, right?
And so, you know, as
long as the scope doesn't
change, right, then the price is just set.
That's it.
That's the most common type.
It's the most common type of fixed price
contract, FFP, firm fixed price price.
Then you have this one called the F-P-I-F.
Make sure you know all these acronyms as
well, F-P-I-F, Fixed
Price with Incentive Fee.
So it's a fixed-price
contract, but then there's
some kind of incentive
fee along with it as well.
The incentive could be in the form of a
bonus.
Typically, that's what an incentive means
could be in the form of a bonus,
but it could also be in the form of a
penalty.
If the seller does not provide this good
or service or provide a particular good,
or service or, you know, they don't
perform in a certain way or they don't
finish by a certain
date, don't meet a certain
milestone, there might be some penalties.
So it gives them the incentive to perform,
you know, to meet that performance goal.
Right.
So the incentive fee then
could be in the form of
a bonus or it could be
in the form of a penalty.
Or it could also be in the form of a cost
share, right, a cost share where buyer and
seller have agreed to share part of the
cost increase.
So you have an estimated cost for the
project, and then you have the maximum cost.
So this is a minimum that
the buyer is going to pay,
and this is a maximum
the buyer is going to pay.
The maximum that the buyer is going to pay
is known as a ceiling price.
Right?
So you have the minimum that the buyer is
going to pay, and the
ceiling price a maximum.
Anything in between is now shared.
Any cost increase in between.
Any cost increase in between is going to
be shared by the buyer and seller.
That's part of the contract.
They're both agreed.
So, for example, it could be an 80 to 20.
80% of the cost increases.
80% of the cost increase is covered by the
buyer.
20% is covered by the seller.
Until we hit the ceiling price,
any cost increase above that ceiling price
now is going to be 100% covered by the
seller.
So that ceiling price
then is a fixed, is a fixed
fee, if you like, or the
fixed price of the contract.
So a fixed price incentive fee,
then, could be in the form of a bonus,
most common, penalty,
not as common, right,
or it could be in the
form of a cost share.
And then you have
this other one, the fixed
price with economic
price adjustment, FPEPA.
Fixed price is economic price adjustment.
And an FPEPA then,
economic price adjustment is
basically things like,
for example, inflation.
It's a multi-year project, right?
It's fixed price, but then there's an
adjustment for inflation.
Or it could take into
account price volatility,
exchange rate, right, and so and so forth.
Basically any economic condition.
So material prices are very volatile right
now.
So it's a fixed price contract,
but then there's an adjustment in case
where material prices
increases by a certain
amount or a certain
percentage and so and so forth.
So generally you will see FPEPA generally
in long-term contracts.
Okay, so these are the different types of
contracts then.
So in this video, right, we discussed the
fixed price contract, right?
In the fixed price contract then,
three variations that you need to know is
a firm fixed price, fixed
price with incentive fee,
and fixed price with
economic price adjustment.
Okay.